<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V4.1.2.5//EN" "../sdocbook.dtd">
<!-- <!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../../../sdocbook.dtd"> -->
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <author><firstname>Alex</firstname><surname>Moffat</surname></author>
    <title>XSLTXT : An alternative XSLT syntax</title>
  </articleinfo>
  <section>

    <title>Why a different syntax?</title>

    <para>The XML syntax for XSLT is very easy to parse, as it's XML,
    relatively easy to read, but tedious to write once you get past
    the simplest transformations. I find that the semantics of XSLT
    get swamped by the syntax of XML. For example, the number of
    characters used for xml markup can be very large compared to the
    number used for the actual semantics of the transformations. For
    example, if you want to write a simple template with a name of foo
    that takes two parameters and generates a statement like
    <command>SELECT x FROM y</command> you can write the template
    element below. This uses approximately 122 characters for markup
    and 22 for meaning.</para>
    
    <programlisting>
      <![CDATA[
<xsl:template name="foo">
  <xsl:param name="a"/>
  <xsl:param name="b"/>
SELECT <xsl:value-of select="$a"/> FROM <xsl:value-of select="$b"/>
</xsl:template>]]>
    </programlisting>

    <para>In contrast the alternative syntax can express this using
    only 31 characters of markup and 22 characters for meaning, as
    shown below. I hope that this makes the meaning clearer and it is
    certainly quicker to write.</para>
    
    <programlisting>
      <![CDATA[
tpl .name "foo" ("a", "b")
  "SELECT "
  val "$a"
  " FROM "
  val "$b"]]>
    </programlisting>

    <para>XSLTXT makes no changes to XSLT semantics. The things that
      are tedious to do in XSLT are still tedious in XSLTXT but at
      least there is less typing. The advantage of this approach is
      that in Java a <command>XMLReader</command> can be constructed
      that will parse an XSLTXT file and produce SAX events as if an
      XSLT file was being processed. XSLTXT can therefore be used in
      place of XSLT without having to build another XSLT
      processor.</para>
      
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Basic principles</title>

    <para>XSLTXT does four things to try to reduce the number of markup
      characters.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>Use indentation to delimit the block structure instead of start and end markers.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>Reduce the length of some of the names used, for example <command>template</command> becomes <command>tpl</command>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>Required attributes no longer have attribute names, instead they are positional.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>In some situations <command>param</command> and
      <command>with-param</command> statements can be written using
      parentheses.
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    
    <para>An XSLTXT stylesheet is made up of statements, modifiers,
    comments, quoted text, XML elements, and whitespace.</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
	<term>Statements</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Statements correspond to the elements in XSLT such as
    <command>&lt;xsl:apply-templates/&gt;</command>. They often have
    the same name as the element they represent. In some cases though
    a shorter name is used to help make it easier to write and read
    XSLTXT.</para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	<term>Modifiers</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Modifiers correspond to the optional attributes of the
    XSLT elements. They are written with a leading period, and are
    generally named the same as the attribute they represent. For
    example, the <command>mode</command> attribute is represented by
    the <command>.mode</command> modifier. The value of the attribute
    is written as a quoted string following the modifier. So the XSLT
    element <command>&lt;xsl:apply-templates
    select="author/given-name"/&gt;</command> would be represented by
    the XSLTXT statement <command>apply .select
    "author/given-name"</command></para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	<term>Comments</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Comments start with a # as the first non whitespace character
	  on a line and proceed to the end of the line.</para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	<term>Quoted text</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>The value of any modifier or any text to be output must be
	  surrounded by &quot;. This is not the same as XSLT where any
	  text not recognized as an XML element is output.</para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	<term>XML elements</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>You can include XML elements in the stylesheet just as in
	  XSL. However, you should not write the close element. For example in XSL
	  you might write</para>
	  <programlisting>
            <![CDATA[
<first-name>Bob</first-name>]]>
	  </programlisting>
	  <para>but in XSLTXT you would write</para>
	  <programlisting>
	    <![CDATA[
<first-name>
  "Bob"]]>
	  </programlisting>
	  <para>instead as indentation is used to show the block structure of
	  the element.</para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	<term>Whitespace</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>is ignored</para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    
    <para>As with XSLT some XSLTXT statements can
      <emphasis>contain</emphasis> other statments. XSLTXT uses
      indentation to mark its block structure in a similar way to
      Python and Haskell so it does not need the end element markers
      of XML. A XSLTXT statement includes all those statements whose
    indentation is greater than it's own indentation. For example in the two
    templates below</para>

    <programlisting>
      <![CDATA[
tpl .mode "client"
  "Client "
  val "@name"
      
tpl .mode "server"
  "Server "
  val "@host"  ]]>      
    </programlisting>

    <para>It can be seen from the indentation that the first, with
      <command>.mode "client"</command>, contains the string
      <command>"Client "</command> and the statement <command>val
      "@name"</command>, while the second, with <command>.mode
      "server"</command> contains the string <command>"Server
      "</command> and the statement <command>val
      "@host"</command>.</para>
      
    <para>Statements, modifiers and comments in XSLTXT are written
      without quotes. Everything else is written in quotes.</para>
    
    <para>Required attributes need no modifier, just a value. For example
    the <command>import</command> element has a required attribute
    <command>href</command>. In XSLTXT the value for this attribute
    is placed directly after the statement with no modifier. So,
    <command><![CDATA[<xsl:import href="others.xsl"/>]]></command> becomes
    <command>import "others.txt"</command> If a statement has more than
    one required attribute they must be entered in the correct order.</para>

    <para>Optional attributes are preceeded by their name with a
    period in front of it, for example the mode attribute of a
    template statement would be written <command>.mode
    "myMode"</command></para>

    <para>Parameters, whether expressed in xsl as
    <command>param</command> or <command>with-param</command> can be
    represented in XSLTXT in two ways. The representation used
    depends on how any parameter value is represented. The first
    representation can be chosen if all of the
    <command>param</command> or <command>with-param</command>
    statements either have no value, use the <command>select</command>
    attribute to provide a value, or if there value is only a text
    string. This representation surrounds the parameters with
    <command>(</command> and <command>)</command> and separates each
    parameter name from its value, if it has one, with a
    <command>:</command>jif the value is a select or a
    <command>%</command> if the value is to be used as a text
    value. So,</para>

    <programlisting>
      <![CDATA[
<xsl:template name="bySize">
  <xsl:param name="height" select="@height"/>
  <xsl:param name="weight" select="@weight"/>
  <xsl:value-of select="$height"/> * <xsl:value-of select="$weight"/>    
</xsl:template> ]]>
    </programlisting>

    <para>would be shown in XSLTXT as</para>

    <programlisting>
      <![CDATA[
tpl .name "bySize" ("height":"@height", "weight":"@weight")
  val "$height"
  " * "
  val "$weight" ]]>
    </programlisting>

    <para>and a call to this template could be written</para>

    <programlisting>
      <![CDATA[
call "bySize" ("height":"@height", "weight"%"100")]]>
    </programlisting>

    <para>if the weight was going to be passed as a string with a
      value of 100. This would be written in xslt as</para>

    <programlisting>
      <![CDATA[
<xsl:call-template name="bySize">
  <xsl:with-param name="height" select="@height"/>
  <xsl:with-param name="weight">
    <xsl:text>100</xsl:text>
  </xsl:with-param>
</xsl:call-template>]]>
    </programlisting>

    <para>If a parameter does not have a default value then the
    <command>:</command> or <command>%</command> is not required. So
    <command><![CDATA[<xsl:param name="foo"/>]]></command> would become
    <command>("foo")</command></para>
	
    <para>Handling of <command>import</command> and
    <command>include</command> statements. During conversion from
    XSLTXT to XSLT or vise versa the extension on urls being imported
    or includes is swapped.</para>
    
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Using the alternative syntax.</title>
    <section>
      <title>Converting from XSLTXT to XSLT.</title>
      
      <para>In the directory
	<command>src/com/zanthan/xsltxt/examples</command> is an
	example called <command>TXTConverter.java</command> that
	demonstrates how to convert from XSLTXT to XSL. It has comments to
	explain what the steps are and should form a good basis if you
	want to program something similar yourself.</para>

    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Converting from XML to XSLTXT.</title>

      <para>In the directory
	<command>src/com/zanthan/xsltxt/examples</command> is an
	example called <command>XSLConverter.java</command> that
	demonstrates how to convert from XSL to XSLTXT. It has
	comments to explain what the steps are and should form a good
	basis if you want to program something similar
	yourself. </para>

    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Using XSLTXT in place of XSLT via TXTReader.</title>

      <para>In the directory
	<command>src/com/zanthan/xsltxt/examples</command> is an
	example called <command>TXTStyler.java</command>. This
	demonstrates how to use a TXTReaderTwo instance to process an
	XSLTXT file directly into xsl style sheets.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
</article>  